Here we have once again the
activity diagram we have just seen.
Let's take a look at
which actions, i.e. which sequences
of individual steps, are described by it.
I already said that this reminds us
a bit of a flat state diagram.
In fact, to find our way around,
we will borrow the notion
of tokens from Petri nets.
We're going to
represent the position where
we are in the activity diagram during
execution with a token of some sort.
That's why I prepared this.
So we can imagine that we start with a
token at the beginning, that's this node that stands
for the start of the activity diagram.
Then we use a token like that.
We don't put it directly on the
circles like in the Petri net, but we
note it here, next to this action node,
as it will be called in a moment.
Then a first step here would
have to be to choose a
building site, because we
simply followed the first arrow.
As ultimately pretend here, through this
first link in the activity diagram.
Then it is also clear that we
will probably continue to follow these arrows.
The next step would then have to
be that we look for an architect.
And then here comes such a node, which,
as we can already see from the incoming
and outgoing arrows, probably
branches or connects things.
In the specific case, we come
in through this arrow, there's another way
to come in here, but we
come in on this side now.
And the only outgoing arrow would be
that we go on, to create plan.
So then we would be
here by just following this path.
Then there's this other kind of node
here now that's shown a little bit differently.
Before we had this oval node,
here we have this rectangular node.
This would actually be something like a place
in the Petri net where something can be deposited.
Where if necessary also, if there were
several entrances, for example, several plans could lie.
You could say, so far
this token was mainly there to
somehow mark a sequence or
to mark a current position.
In this object node we have here,
"plan", you could also imagine that
this token is a concrete plan.
If we had multiple tokens
later, then maybe there would be
multiple plans moving
through this system.
So a plan was created, now we
have a plan, what happens to that?
Well the outgoing arrow would be
to the next action, submit a plan.
Then it turns out, after
that there's another node like that,
but now it has one input and two outputs.
That is, here it would be a place where
there seems to be a choice about what happens.
The choice has an effect in
that there are these conditions here.
These are conditions on the plan.
This token represents a specific plan
that was previously created,
then submitted and reviewed.
And now there can
be two possible outcomes, namely:
This plan is accepted or not.
That's represented by
this notation here, which
has to be somehow
evidenced from the application.
Somewhere there has to be a term
for a plan, whether it's acceptable or not.
That's not further specified
by the diagram here, that
simply uses the result of such a review.
And let's assume that the specific plan
that we have here would in fact
not be accepted, then we
would just move on here.
And thus arrive again
at this this node, which
again has only one possible outcome, which is
that a new plan would have to be created.
Then we already see that this can go on,
a new plan is submitted and reviewed.
Then it might happen that we
have to go through this circle
again and at some point we
might have a plan that is acceptable.
Then we would take that
exit, then we would be here
now with our plan, with our token.
Now what's the deal
with this particular kind of
node, or element
in this activity diagram?
Well this is a place where not
only a path crossing takes place, in
the sense that a direction changes where a
token can go, like on the node before.
But actually a splitting
of tokens takes place.
We end up with one input and two outputs.
This is different from the step before,
where one of the two outputs is taken.
But here, with the bar, the so-called
forking, it is to be understood actually in
such a way that this token is
divided now two. So we have the
idea, like with Petri nets, that we
can just have more than one token.
So it's not enough, as
in a flat state diagram, to
just point to a node and
say here we are right now.
Because of this splitting of
tokens it is more interesting now.
We're not going left or right.
But rather we go left and right
the next actions at the same time.
That's not what a
flat state diagram allows.
In our wolf-goat-carbon-head problem there was
no such thing, in this constellation.
What is meant here is that
these two actions "work on the
construction site" and "work in the
office" take place concurrently with the plan.
The order does not matter.
Both must happen, but it is not
given in which order. It could be that
work on the construction site takes place first and
then work in the office, or vice versa,
or factually at the same time after all.
The point is,
these are independent operations.
Let's assume both were performed.
Then we would be at this element,
which obviously looks like the opposite of this.
Because now there are two
inputs and one output arrow.
And actually this is the synchronization
point, so here these
two tokens would merge again.
For this they both have to be there.
So if the one token would still
be here, the other token can't progress here.
But if both tokens in
these two concurrent processes have
arrived down here, then they
can and must merge here again.
Then there would be only
one token again from now on.
Then the house could be finished.
Then the flow, here,
would end at this place.
Since this special node stands for the
fact that the river ends, and there
are also no further exit arrows from there.
So you can first approach,
intuitively, such an activity diagram.
Of course, you still have to
explain what exactly these individual elements mean.
That was just an example, but it
might be a good illustration
of what is happening here.
This token concept, the idea that
a flow can split or unite, and
before that, through this kind of
node, alternatives can be represented here.
So, it has something of a flat state
diagram, but is more
through the additional elements.
It also has a bit of
a Petri net, through this token concept.
Still, it makes sense to
not just take Petri nets,
but to use these
activity diagrams in practice.
Because of the different elements
that occur, each of which has
a graphical notation and then an intuitive
meaning, modeling can be easier instead of
trying to implement everything with Petri net means,
where you always just have places and transitions.
We will see later that one can
also specify a Petri net for this.
But we will see that we need more nodes,
more places and transitions
than there were elements now.
This is due to the fact
that these elements, like this one for
example, already have a very special meaning, which
one must first reconstruct with the Petri net,
and it cannot necessarily be
done with exactly one node.
It's a question of expressiveness.
We often had in Petri
nets many places and transitions,
which did not have a
meaningful name for each of them.
Whereas here we can assign
a meaningful name to each element.
Every element that appears here also has
a meaning in the application being modeled.
And there are also these very special
elements, like this
forking and this synchronization/merge.